<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-10T14:45:07-05:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Northern Robotics Laboratory</title><subtitle>Website showcasing research and news from the Northern Robotics Laboratory, Laval University</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Improving the Iterative Closest Point Algorithm using Lie Algebra</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/icp-lie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving the Iterative Closest Point Algorithm using Lie Algebra" /><published>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/icp-lie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/icp-lie/">&lt;p&gt;Mapping algorithms that rely on registering point clouds inevitably suffer from local drift, both in localization and in the built map.
Applications that require accurate maps, such as environmental monitoring, benefit from additional sensor modalities that reduce such drift.
In our work, we target the family of mappers based on the ICP algorithm which use additional orientation sources such as the IMU.
We introduce a new angular penalty term derived from Lie algebra.
Our formulation avoids the need for tuning arbitrary parameters.
Orientation covariance is used instead, and the resulting error term fits into the ICP cost function minimization problem.
%In this extended abstract, we also present the experimental work in progress.
Experiments performed on our own real-world data and on the KITTI dataset show consistent behavior while suppressing the effect of outlying IMU measurements.
We further discuss promising experiments, which should lead to optimal combination of all error terms in the ICP cost function minimization problem, allowing us to smoothly combine the geometric and inertial information provided by robot sensors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;contributions&quot;&gt;Contributions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The formulation of a novel penalty on the ICP process using Lie algebra, leading to more accurate maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-in-images&quot;&gt;Results in Images&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the performance of our method, we tested our algorithm in a snowy environment at the Laval University.
During this experiment, the robot was performing high-velocity trajectories:
because of the low friction of the snow, the robot was considerably skidding and slipping and thus generating incorrect odometry prior.
Due to the high velocity, the distance between subsequent point clouds can be large and with wrong prior, the ICP can fall into local minimum by wandering too far away from the orientation prior.
The figure below shows two computed trajectories for the same experiment, with and without our rotational penalty.
On the trajectory computed without the penalty (left), two breaking points can be seen at the top and bottom part of the picture, meaning that the ICP converged to a wrong solution.
With the Lie penalty (right), these breaking points are avoided as this term pushes the ICP to converge quicker to the right solution while avoiding local minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/publications/icp-lie/comparison_trajectory.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Vaidis2020&quot;&gt;Vaidis, M., Laconte, J., Kubelka, V., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Improving the Iterative Closest Point Algorithm using Lie Algebra. &lt;i&gt;IROS 2020 Workshop - Bringing Geometric Methods to Robot Learning, Optimization and Control&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.11160&quot;&gt;Download article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Johann Laconte</name></author><category term="publications" /><category term="ICP" /><category term="mapping" /><summary type="html">Mapping algorithms that rely on registering point clouds inevitably suffer from local drift, both in localization and in the built map. Applications that require accurate maps, such as environmental monitoring, benefit from additional sensor modalities that reduce such drift. In our work, we target the family of mappers based on the ICP algorithm which use additional orientation sources such as the IMU. We introduce a new angular penalty term derived from Lie algebra. Our formulation avoids the need for tuning arbitrary parameters. Orientation covariance is used instead, and the resulting error term fits into the ICP cost function minimization problem. %In this extended abstract, we also present the experimental work in progress. Experiments performed on our own real-world data and on the KITTI dataset show consistent behavior while suppressing the effect of outlying IMU measurements. We further discuss promising experiments, which should lead to optimal combination of all error terms in the ICP cost function minimization problem, allowing us to smoothly combine the geometric and inertial information provided by robot sensors. Contributions</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22publications/icp-lie_teaser.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22publications/icp-lie_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22publications/icp-lie_teaser.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22publications/icp-lie_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Damien LaRocque</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Damien LaRocque" /><published>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque/">&lt;p&gt;Damien LaRocque is a master student at Norlab, under the supervision of Pr. &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He graduated with a bachelor’s degree in Electrical Engineering at the Université de Moncton in 2020. During his bachelor’s degree, he actively contributed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grumoncton.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groupe de Robotique de Université de Moncton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (GRUM), whose goal is to design autonomous mobile robots to represent Canada at the international robotics competition &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurobot.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eurobot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. With the GRUM, he has developed computer vision and localization algorithms allowing their robots to accomplish agility tasks and accumulate points against teams from around fifteen countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also completed an internship at &lt;a href=&quot;https://robot.gmc.ulaval.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laboratoire de robotique de l’Université Laval&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; under the supervision of Pr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://robot.gmc.ulaval.ca/membres/membres-actuels/clement-gosselin/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Clément Gosselin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His work on the &lt;a href=&quot;../../research/snow&quot;&gt;SNOW project&lt;/a&gt; mainly consists in improving and developing path planning methods for autonomous navigation of mobile robots in complex winter conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bachelor’s degree in Electrical Engineering from University of Moncton, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- # Publications

 --&gt;</content><author><name>Damien LaRocque</name><email>damien.larocque@norlab.ulaval.ca</email></author><summary type="html">Damien LaRocque is a master student at Norlab, under the supervision of Pr. François Pomerleau.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque_avatar.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque_avatar.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Damien LaRocque</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque_fr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Damien LaRocque" /><published>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque_fr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/d_larocque_fr/">&lt;p&gt;Damien LaRocque est un étudiant à la maîtrise au sein du Norlab sous la supervision du P&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il est gradué du baccalauréat en génie électrique à l’Université de Moncton en 2020. Durant son baccalauréat, il a contribué activement au &lt;a href=&quot;https://grumoncton.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groupe de Robotique de l’Université de Moncton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (GRUM), dont le but est de concevoir des robots mobiles autonomes pour représenter le Canada à la compétition internationale de robotique &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurobot.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eurobot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Auprès du GRUM, il a développé des algorithmes de vision par ordinateur et de localisation de robots permettant à ceux-ci d’accomplir des tâches d’agilité et d’accumuler des points face à des équipes venant d’une quinzaine de pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il a également réalisé un stage au sein du &lt;a href=&quot;https://robot.gmc.ulaval.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laboratoire de robotique de l’Université Laval&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sous la supervision du P&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://robot.gmc.ulaval.ca/membres/membres-actuels/clement-gosselin/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Clément Gosselin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Son travail sur le &lt;a href=&quot;../../research/snow&quot;&gt;projet SNOW&lt;/a&gt; consiste principalement à améliorer et développer des méthodes de planification de trajectoires pour la navigation autonome de robots mobiles en conditions hivernales complexes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baccalauréat en génie électrique à l’Université de Moncton, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- # Publications

 --&gt;</content><author><name>Damien LaRocque</name><email>damien.larocque@norlab.ulaval.ca</email></author><summary type="html">Damien LaRocque est un étudiant à la maîtrise au sein du Norlab sous la supervision du Pr François Pomerleau.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque_avatar.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/d_larocque_avatar.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Geometry Preserving Sampling Method based on Spectral Decomposition for Large-scale Environments</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/map-compression/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Geometry Preserving Sampling Method based on Spectral Decomposition for Large-scale Environments" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/map-compression</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/map-compression/">&lt;p&gt;In the context of 3D mapping, larger and larger point clouds are acquired with lidar sensors.
Although pleasing to the eye, dense maps are not necessarily tailored for practical applications.
For instance, in a surface inspection scenario, keeping geometric information such as the edges of objects is essential to detect cracks, whereas very dense areas of very little information such as the ground could hinder the main goal of the application. 
Several strategies exist to address this problem by reducing the number of points.
However, they tend to underperform with non-uniform density, large sensor noise, spurious measurements, and large-scale point clouds, which is the case in mobile robotics.
This paper presents a novel sampling algorithm based on spectral decomposition analysis to derive local density measures for each geometric primitive.
The proposed method, called Spectral Decomposition Filter (SpDF), identifies and preserves geometric information along the topology of point clouds and is able to scale to large environments with a non-uniform density.
Finally, qualitative and quantitative experiments verify the feasibility of our method and present a large-scale evaluation of SpDF with other seven point cloud sampling algorithms, in the context of the 3D registration problem using the Iterative Closest Point (ICP) algorithm on real-world datasets.
Results show that a compression ratio up to 97% can be achieved when accepting a registration error within the range accuracy of the sensor, here for large scale environments of less than 2cm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;contributions&quot;&gt;Contributions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A novel sampling method, called Spectral Decomposition Filter (SpDF), based on spectral decomposition analysis. This method identifies and preserves geometric information along the topology of point clouds and is scalable to large environments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A large-scale evaluation of current sampling strategies relying on more than 2.45 million registrations in different types of environments (indoor/structured, outdoor/unstructured), including large-scale outdoors environments from real-world datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-in-images&quot;&gt;Results in Images&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, we created the map of the Grand Axe of Laval University campus, where only a few minutes of data collection lead to a number of points at the limit of the real-time computation capability. 
The sensor used for this map, the Velodyne HDL-32E, yields up to 1.39 million points per second.
Using our sampling algorithm, the map is compressed at 98%, while preserving geometrical information.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/publications/map-compression/laval.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the voxel method suffers from the discrepancy between the x, y and z scales, as it creates the bounding box with a radius of the size of the bigger dimension. 
Furthermore, as the ground is not aligned with the xy-plane, it keeps points which are at different altitudes within the dense path.
Finally, when geometric details are not dense enough such as the pillars of the top-left of the map, the voxel method does not keep them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/publications/map-compression/subviews.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Labussiere2020&quot;&gt;Labussière, M., Laconte, J., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Geometry Preserving Sampling Method based on Spectral Decomposition for Large-scale Environments. &lt;i&gt;Frontiers in Robotics and AI – Multi-Robot Systems&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;7&lt;/i&gt;, 134. https://doi.org/10.3389/frobt.2020.572054&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/frobt.2020.572054/&quot;&gt;Download article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.asl.ethz.ch/datasets/doku.php?id=laserregistration:laserregistration&quot;&gt;Details on dataset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Johann Laconte</name></author><category term="publications" /><category term="ICP" /><category term="lidar" /><category term="mapping" /><category term="sampling" /><summary type="html">In the context of 3D mapping, larger and larger point clouds are acquired with lidar sensors. Although pleasing to the eye, dense maps are not necessarily tailored for practical applications. For instance, in a surface inspection scenario, keeping geometric information such as the edges of objects is essential to detect cracks, whereas very dense areas of very little information such as the ground could hinder the main goal of the application. Several strategies exist to address this problem by reducing the number of points. However, they tend to underperform with non-uniform density, large sensor noise, spurious measurements, and large-scale point clouds, which is the case in mobile robotics. This paper presents a novel sampling algorithm based on spectral decomposition analysis to derive local density measures for each geometric primitive. The proposed method, called Spectral Decomposition Filter (SpDF), identifies and preserves geometric information along the topology of point clouds and is able to scale to large environments with a non-uniform density. Finally, qualitative and quantitative experiments verify the feasibility of our method and present a large-scale evaluation of SpDF with other seven point cloud sampling algorithms, in the context of the 3D registration problem using the Iterative Closest Point (ICP) algorithm on real-world datasets. Results show that a compression ratio up to 97% can be achieved when accepting a registration error within the range accuracy of the sensor, here for large scale environments of less than 2cm. Contributions</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22publications/map-compression_teaser.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22publications/map-compression_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22publications/map-compression_teaser.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22publications/map-compression_feature.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Simon-Pierre Deschênes</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simon-Pierre Deschênes" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes/">&lt;p&gt;Simon-Pierre Deschênes is a PhD student at Norlab, under the supervision of Pr. &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt;.
After his internship in the laboratory in summer 2018 as part of his bachelor’s degree, Simon-Pierre was captivated by 3D mapping and decided to continue his graduate studies in this field.
His research project is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;../../research/snow&quot;&gt;SNOW project&lt;/a&gt; and focuses on 3D localization and mapping in harsh winter conditions using the ICP algorithm.
The participation of the different project members allowed them to meet and even go beyond the first milestone objectives. 
Here is a demonstration of the system that has been implemented in the scope of the project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LILvVsYoaAg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last, Simon-Pierre has participated in several other projects since his arrival in the laboratory, including the 2019 christmas video of Norlab, which he directed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uNiGKETYOjQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Master’s degree in computer science (fast-track to PhD), 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bachelor’s degree in software engineering at Laval University, 2019&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;publications&quot;&gt;Publications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Conference Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot; reversed=&quot;reversed&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Baril2020&quot;&gt;Baril, D., Grondin, V., Deschênes, S., Laconte, J., M., V., Kubelka, V., Gallant, A., Giguère, P., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments. &lt;i&gt;Proceeding of the 2020 17th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/Baril2020.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;details&quot; href=&quot;/bibliography/Baril2020/&quot;&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-code&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bibtex source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Laconte2019&quot;&gt;Laconte, J., Deschênes, S.-P., Labussière, M., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2019). Lidar Measurement Bias Estimation via Return Waveform Modelling in a Context of 3D Mapping. &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/Laconte2019.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;details&quot; href=&quot;/bibliography/Laconte2019/&quot;&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-code&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bibtex source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Simon-Pierre Deschênes</name><email>simon-pierre.deschenes.1@ulaval.ca</email></author><summary type="html">Simon-Pierre Deschênes is a PhD student at Norlab, under the supervision of Pr. François Pomerleau. After his internship in the laboratory in summer 2018 as part of his bachelor’s degree, Simon-Pierre was captivated by 3D mapping and decided to continue his graduate studies in this field. His research project is part of the SNOW project and focuses on 3D localization and mapping in harsh winter conditions using the ICP algorithm. The participation of the different project members allowed them to meet and even go beyond the first milestone objectives. Here is a demonstration of the system that has been implemented in the scope of the project:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes_avatar.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes_avatar.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Simon-Pierre Deschênes</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes_fr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simon-Pierre Deschênes" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes_fr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/people/sp_deschenes_fr/">&lt;p&gt;Simon-Pierre Deschênes est un étudiant au doctorat au sein du Norlab sous la supervision du Pr. &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt;.
Ayant effectué un stage au sein du laboratoire à l’été 2018 dans le cadre de son baccalauréat, Simon-Pierre a été captivé par la cartographie 3D et a décidé de poursuivre ses études supérieures dans ce domaine.
Son projet de recherche s’insère dans le &lt;a href=&quot;../../research/snow&quot;&gt;projet SNOW&lt;/a&gt; et porte sur la cartographie et la localisation 3D en conditions hivernales diffiles à l’aide de l’algorithme ICP.
La participation des différents membres du projet leur a permis d’atteindre et même de surpasser les objectifs du premier jalon.
Voici une démonstration du système mis en place dans le cadre de ce projet :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LILvVsYoaAg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enfin, Simon-Pierre a participé à plusieurs autres projets depuis son arrivée au laboratoire, dont le vidéo de Noël 2019 du Norlab dont il a dirigé la réalisation :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uNiGKETYOjQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maîtrise en informatique à l’Université Laval (passage accéléré au doctorat), 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baccalauréat en génie logiciel à l’Université Laval, 2019&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;publications&quot;&gt;Publications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Conference Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot; reversed=&quot;reversed&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Baril2020&quot;&gt;Baril, D., Grondin, V., Deschênes, S., Laconte, J., M., V., Kubelka, V., Gallant, A., Giguère, P., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments. &lt;i&gt;Proceeding of the 2020 17th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/Baril2020.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;details&quot; href=&quot;/bibliography/Baril2020/&quot;&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-code&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bibtex source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Laconte2019&quot;&gt;Laconte, J., Deschênes, S.-P., Labussière, M., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2019). Lidar Measurement Bias Estimation via Return Waveform Modelling in a Context of 3D Mapping. &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/Laconte2019.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;details&quot; href=&quot;/bibliography/Laconte2019/&quot;&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-code&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bibtex source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Simon-Pierre Deschênes</name><email>simon-pierre.deschenes.1@ulaval.ca</email></author><summary type="html">Simon-Pierre Deschênes est un étudiant au doctorat au sein du Norlab sous la supervision du Pr. François Pomerleau. Ayant effectué un stage au sein du laboratoire à l’été 2018 dans le cadre de son baccalauréat, Simon-Pierre a été captivé par la cartographie 3D et a décidé de poursuivre ses études supérieures dans ce domaine. Son projet de recherche s’insère dans le projet SNOW et porte sur la cartographie et la localisation 3D en conditions hivernales diffiles à l’aide de l’algorithme ICP. La participation des différents membres du projet leur a permis d’atteindre et même de surpasser les objectifs du premier jalon. Voici une démonstration du système mis en place dans le cadre de ce projet :</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes_avatar.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/people/sp_deschenes_avatar.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Norlab goes to CRV!</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/news/crv20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norlab goes to CRV!" /><published>2020-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/news/crv20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/news/crv20/">&lt;p&gt;This month, the lab attended the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computerrobotvision.org/&quot;&gt;17th conference on Computer and Robot Vision&lt;/a&gt;, which was held virtually due to the COVID-19 situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We presented our article on kinematic motion modelling for skid-steering mobile robots in subartic environments &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#Baril2020&quot;&gt;(Baril et al., 2020)&lt;/a&gt;. More details on our article can be found &lt;a href=&quot;../../publications/subartic_kinematic_modelling&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The paper was awarded with the “Best robotics paper” award for the conference. The laboratory director, &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt; also gave a symposium presentation on subterranean and subartic autonomous exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Videos for both presentations can be found below :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2ebxortAhmE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fjSwHVdnzLQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-articles&quot;&gt;Our articles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot; reversed=&quot;reversed&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Baril2020&quot;&gt;Baril, D., Grondin, V., Deschênes, S., Laconte, J., M., V., Kubelka, V., Gallant, A., Giguère, P., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments. &lt;i&gt;Proceeding of the 2020 17th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/Baril2020.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PDF&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a class=&quot;details&quot; href=&quot;/bibliography/Baril2020/&quot;&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-file-code&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bibtex source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Dominic Baril</name><email>dominic.baril@norlab.ulaval.ca</email></author><category term="conference" /><summary type="html">This month, the lab attended the 17th conference on Computer and Robot Vision, which was held virtually due to the COVID-19 situation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/news/crv20/news_crv2020.jpeg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/news/crv20/news_crv2020.jpeg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to synchronize an Overleaf Project with a GitHub repository</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/latex-github-overleaf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to synchronize an Overleaf Project with a GitHub repository" /><published>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/latex-github-overleaf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/latex-github-overleaf/">&lt;p&gt;Writing papers with a large number of co-authors can be complicated endeavour. This why &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overleaf.com/&quot;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting choice, as it allows for multiple people to edit a same LaTeX document simultaneously. However, online compiling on Overleaf requires time and you will also want to have access to your files on your laptop and use your favorite LaTeX editor. This is why synchronizing your paper in an Overleaf project as well as in a GitHub repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. This will also grant you access to the laboratory’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norlab-ulaval/latexGoodPractices&quot;&gt;LaTeX good practices repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;main-reasons-why-you-will-want-to-synchronize-your-paper-on-github-and-overleaf&quot;&gt;Main reasons why you will want to synchronize your paper on Github and Overleaf&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows for multiple contributors to work on a project simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows to backup and archive your paper in the common laboratory repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows to easily export your paper in &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt; friendly format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;procedure&quot;&gt;Procedure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In your Overleaf dashboard, create a new blank project using &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_new_project.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 20%&quot; /&gt; and give it a relevant name (e.g., publication_conference/journal_name_firstnameLastname)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the project page on Overleaf, select &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_menu.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 12%&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_github.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 30%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Create a Github repository”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Select “norlab-ulaval” as Owner and select the “Private” option so you can choose who can commit to the repository&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The repository should now be visible on the laboratory’s GitHub page :&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norlab-ulaval&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;btn&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/logos/github.svg&quot; style=&quot;padding-right: 1em; width: 4em; -webkit-filter: invert(100%); filter: invert(100%);&quot; /&gt;
norlab-ulaval
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository on you computer&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone &amp;lt;github_repo_url&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norlab-ulaval/latexGoodPractices&quot;&gt;LaTeX good practices repository&lt;/a&gt; as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Submodules&quot;&gt;Git submodule&lt;/a&gt;, as shown below :&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git submodule add https://github.com/norlab-ulaval/latexGoodPractices.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push the changes from your local repository to the remote GitHub repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pull the changes from the Overleaf project page by selecting &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_menu.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 12%&quot; /&gt; , &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_github.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 30%&quot; /&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/pull_overleaf.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 35%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your project is now synchronized between the two platforms and you can now push or pull changes directly from the Overleaf project page. Be careful when editing the document on your laptop at the same time as it is being changed on Overleaf as this may cause merging conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;exporting-an-article-using-overleaf&quot;&gt;Exporting an article using Overleaf&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main advantages of using this method for your projects is that Overleaf offers a tool to export your project for numerous publishing platforms, notably &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/&quot;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. Simply compile your project once it is completed and select &lt;img src=&quot;/images/github_overleaf_sync/overleaf_submit.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 12%&quot; /&gt; tab on the top left of the project page. Then select the platform where you wish to publish and Overleaf will create the necessary files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that an issue related to the biblatex file format is likely to happen when compiling the project on arXiv. This issue can be resolved by cloning &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/djsutherland/arxiv-collector&quot;&gt;this Python script&lt;/a&gt; in your local repository and following the instructions to create a biblatex file that is compatible with arXiv. More details on this issue can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/plk/biblatex/wiki/biblatex-and-the-arXiv#uploading-the-relevant-parts-of-biblatex&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dominic Baril</name><email>dominic.baril@norlab.ulaval.ca</email></author><category term="howto" /><category term="Overleaf" /><category term="GitHub" /><category term="LaTeX" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html">Writing papers with a large number of co-authors can be complicated endeavour. This why Overleaf is an interesting choice, as it allows for multiple people to edit a same LaTeX document simultaneously. However, online compiling on Overleaf requires time and you will also want to have access to your files on your laptop and use your favorite LaTeX editor. This is why synchronizing your paper in an Overleaf project as well as in a GitHub repository GitHub. This will also grant you access to the laboratory’s LaTeX good practices repository.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/logos/github_overleaf.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/logos/github_overleaf.png%22,%20%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/subartic_kinematic_modelling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments" /><published>2020-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/subartic_kinematic_modelling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/publications/subartic_kinematic_modelling/">&lt;p&gt;In subarctic and arctic areas, large and heavy skid-steered robots are preferred for their robustness and ability to operate on difficult terrain. State estimation, motion control and path planning for these robots rely on accurate odometry models based on wheel velocities. However, the state-of-the-art odometry models for skid-steer mobile robots (SSMRs) have usually been tested on relatively lightweight platforms. In this paper, we focus on how these models perform when deployed on a large and heavy (590 kg) SSMR. We collected more than 2 km of data on both snow and concrete. We compare the ideal differential-drive, extended differential-drive, radius-of-curvature-based, and full linear kinematic models commonly deployed for SSMRs. Each of the models is fine-tuned by searching their optimal parameters on both snow and concrete. We then discuss the relationship between the parameters, the model tuning, and the final accuracy of the models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quick-facts&quot;&gt;Quick facts:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 Trajectories of more than 2 km were used to train and validate 5 kinematic models for SSMRs on dry concrete and snow-covered terrain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearpathrobotics.com/warthog-unmanned-ground-vehicle-robot/&quot;&gt;Clearpath Robotics Warthog&lt;/a&gt; unmanned ground vehicle was used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extensive analysis of model parameter training is given in the results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our paper is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.05131&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was presented at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computerrobotvision.org/&quot;&gt;17th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2ebxortAhmE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Baril2020&quot;&gt;Baril, D., Grondin, V., Deschênes, S., Laconte, J., M., V., Kubelka, V., Gallant, A., Giguère, P., &amp;amp; Pomerleau, F. (2020). Evaluation of Skid-Steering Kinematic Models for Subarctic Environments. &lt;i&gt;Proceeding of the 2020 17th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dominic Baril</name><email>dominic.baril@norlab.ulaval.ca</email></author><category term="mobile  robots" /><category term="skid-steering  vehicles" /><category term="robot  kinematics" /><category term="winter" /><summary type="html">In subarctic and arctic areas, large and heavy skid-steered robots are preferred for their robustness and ability to operate on difficult terrain. State estimation, motion control and path planning for these robots rely on accurate odometry models based on wheel velocities. However, the state-of-the-art odometry models for skid-steer mobile robots (SSMRs) have usually been tested on relatively lightweight platforms. In this paper, we focus on how these models perform when deployed on a large and heavy (590 kg) SSMR. We collected more than 2 km of data on both snow and concrete. We compare the ideal differential-drive, extended differential-drive, radius-of-curvature-based, and full linear kinematic models commonly deployed for SSMRs. Each of the models is fine-tuned by searching their optimal parameters on both snow and concrete. We then discuss the relationship between the parameters, the model tuning, and the final accuracy of the models.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22projects/subartic_kinematic_modelling_feature.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22projects/subartic_kinematic_modelling_teaser.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22projects/subartic_kinematic_modelling_feature.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22projects/subartic_kinematic_modelling_teaser.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3Enil%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Project SNOW</title><link href="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/snow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project SNOW" /><published>2020-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/snow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/research/snow/">&lt;p&gt;Self-driving cars are expected on our roads soon. In the project SNOW (Self-driving Navigation Optimized for Winter), we focus on the unexplored problem of autonomous driving during winter that still raises reliability concerns. We have the expertise to automatically build 3D maps of the environment while moving through it with robots. We aim at using this knowledge to investigate mapping and control solutions for challenging conditions related to Canadian weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this project is to extend the current technology used for autonomous driving toward unstructured and dynamic environments generated by winter conditions (e.g., a snow-covered forest). This project is addressing the applications of autonomous driving in remote areas, autonomous refueling, search and rescue missions, Canadian Arctic Sovereignty, freight transport on Northern ice roads, etc. Our research concentrates on maps built by a UGV, which will be able to adapt to environmental changes caused by snow and winds, while allowing a robust localization of the vehicle in real-time. These maps will also serve as the foundation for novel path planning algorithms handling deformable obstacles and environments (e.g., deep snow under a vehicle). The project is carried out in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gdlscanada.com/&quot; title=&quot;Official website&quot;&gt;General Dynamics Land Systems - Canada (GDLS-C)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve the goals of the project, the following specific objectives are defined:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective 1—Mapping and Localization:&lt;/strong&gt; to develop algorithms to allow the UGV to localize and
map its environment in winter conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective 2—Path Planning and Control:&lt;/strong&gt; to develop algorithms for planning paths and adapt
the behavior of the UGV according to weather conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective 3—Field Testing and Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; to carry out an extensive series of experiments using
the UGV in a snow-covered forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-theory-to-practice&quot;&gt;From theory to practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows the day we received the UGV - a Warthog robot made by a Canadian company, Clearpath Robotics. We have received the robot in August 2019 and since we began to realize ours plans in practice: 
&lt;!-- blank line --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bmGcV2TA0dY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;integration-of-the-ugv-hardware-and-software&quot;&gt;Integration of the UGV hardware and software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the reception of the UGV, we have had a detailed plan of the tasks to follow to meet our goals, one of them being able to test the robot in a snowy forest during the winter of 2019. The first step was to integrate the sensor suite we had planned for the UGV.  This also involved constructing a solid metal frame by ours hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/snow/forest_3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we finished this electrical part, we continued with the software integration. The mapping software required integration with the system of the UGV, mainly communication with its low-level computer which provides time synchronization and wheel odometry. After finishing all these tasks, it was finally the time to start testing. We found a nice and practical place for initial testing in front of our faculty building. In September 2019 when we fixed all the important details, we were able to proceed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foretmontmorency.ca/en/&quot; title=&quot;Official website&quot;&gt;Montmorency forest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/snow/forest_1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the first tests in the forest was to prove that we could safely deploy the robot, record all necessary data and possibly run mapping on-board the robot computers. We have, of course, discovered some bugs but they were all quick to fix and after a few sessions, we were able to generate large 3D maps of the forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/snow/color_map.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the mapping functionality seemed working fine, we proceeded to implementing a basic path-following functionality. The robot would be navigated once by hand over a desired path while recording its position. Then, a software controller would repeat the path indefinitely, based on the onboard mapping and localization capabilities. The initial tuning of the controller showed some minor oscillations around the learned trajectory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;video width=&quot;80%&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;/images/projects/snow/oscillating.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        Your browser does not support the video tag.
    &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we were able to find the source of the problem, which was a misalignment between the commanded and actually executed turning rate of the robot. After fixing the problem, the controller was able to give us much more satisfying results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;video muted=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;source src=&quot;/images/projects/snow/better_control.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
        Your browser does not support the video tag.
    &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-review-meeting&quot;&gt;First review meeting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of October 2019, the first review meeting took place. It lasted two days and was intended for our partner GDLS-C. We presented the integrated system and its capabilities to allow the partner to replicate the results on their identical UGV. The following video summarizes what was achieved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- blank line --&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LILvVsYoaAg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;team&quot;&gt;Team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principal Investigator and Technical Lead&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/f_pomerleau/&quot;&gt;François Pomerleau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deputy Technical Lead&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/v_kubelka&quot;&gt;Vladimír Kubelka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Representing GDLS-C&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/richard-lee-gdls-ic/&quot;&gt;Richard Lee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PhD students&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/d_baril&quot;&gt;Dominic Baril&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/&quot;&gt;Simon-Pierre Deschênes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Master student&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;../../people/&quot;&gt;Damien LaRocque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;media-coverage&quot;&gt;Media Coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clearpath Robotics&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearpathrobotics.com/blog/2020/10/norlab-pushes-autonomous-navigation-to-limits-with-warthog-ugv/&quot;&gt;Norlab pushes autonomous navigation beyond its limits with Warthog UGV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Jana Bartakova</name></author><category term="project" /><category term="snow" /><category term="robot" /><category term="warthog" /><summary type="html">Self-driving cars are expected on our roads soon. In the project SNOW (Self-driving Navigation Optimized for Winter), we focus on the unexplored problem of autonomous driving during winter that still raises reliability concerns. We have the expertise to automatically build 3D maps of the environment while moving through it with robots. We aim at using this knowledge to investigate mapping and control solutions for challenging conditions related to Canadian weather.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/projects/snow/forest_2_crop.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/projects/snow/snow_teaser.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://norlab.ulaval.ca/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22/projects/snow/forest_2_crop.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%22/projects/snow/snow_teaser.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>